<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A scourge for George Whitehead. An apostate Quaker: an espouser of doctrines and practices tending to Romish-like bondage: a persecuting defamer of the real Christian-Quaker: a publick informer against William Pen, to his defamation: the author of a scandalous book, (written against my seventh part of the Christian-Quaker, &amp;c.) stiled, judgment fixed, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826819</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826819</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31228</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57584)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31228)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1770:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A scourge for George Whitehead. An apostate Quaker: an espouser of doctrines and practices tending to Romish-like bondage: a persecuting defamer of the real Christian-Quaker: a publick informer against William Pen, to his defamation: the author of a scandalous book, (written against my seventh part of the Christian-Quaker, &amp;c.) stiled, judgment fixed, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed, 1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: W.R. (i.e. William Rogers).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Trinity College (University of Cambridge) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:31228:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31228:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SCOURGE FOR <hi>George Whitehead.</hi>
               </hi> An Apoſtate <hi>Quaker:</hi> An Eſpouſer of Doctrines and Practices tending to <hi>Romiſh</hi>-like Bondage: A Perſecuting Defamer of the Real <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker:</hi> A Publick Informer againſt <hi>William Pen,</hi> to his Defamation: The Author of a Scandalous Book, (written againſt my Seventh Part of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> &amp;c.) Stiled, <hi>Judgment Fixed,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe Impartial Reader peruſing the two Books, out of which the enſuing Doctrines are collected, may eaſily be convinced that <hi>G. W.</hi> (if he wanted not Schollarſhip) might (as Author of one, and Approver of t'other) ſooner obtain Preferment at <hi>Rome,</hi> than amongſt the real <hi>Chriſtian Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He owns himſelf to be a Member of a Weekly Meeting, held in <hi>London,</hi> termed, a <hi>Second-days Meeting:</hi> The ſaid <hi>Meeting</hi> have approved <hi>R. B</hi>'s Book of Government, which pretends to ſhew, [<hi>R. B</hi>'s <hi>Anarchy;</hi> Title Page] That, <hi>the Antient, Apoſtolick Order of the Church of Chriſt is Re-eſtabliſh't amongſt the People called</hi> Quakers. And on that foot treats on the Order and Government pleaded for by him and his Brethren: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding one part of the ſaid People diſown all Pretences to the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Eſtabliſhment of, or Subjection to any Outward pretended eſtabliſh't Government over themſelves, as a Society of People; (that only except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, wherein <hi>Charles</hi> the Second now Reigns King of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.) hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prov'd a pretence to an eſtabliſh't Government, I ſhall next note ſome Doctrines; which, as applicable to the Governours, are very pernicious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> G. W. in his <hi>Apoſtate Incendiary,</hi> pag 16. thus aſſerts; <q>I affirm, that the true Church is in the true Faith, that is in God; and we muſt either believe thus, as the true Church believes, or elſe it were but both a Folly and Hypocriſy to profeſs our ſelves Members thereof.</q> And in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31228:2"/> ſame page further ſaith) <q>That he who ſeems to own the Church of Chriſt as a member of her, and yet tells the world that 'tis a moſt dangerous poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that we are to believe as the Church believes, is a <hi>treacherous Enemy</hi> to the Church of Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis averr'd on the behalf of the Church, <q>That they have power to decide and remove differences ariſing between themſelves touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing outward things, and on that occaſion aſſert, not that the aſſent of parties differing ought firſt to be obtained, and therefore the power aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted is abſolute, and the ſentence in Purſuance thereof, definitive; ſince no appeal is declaratively admitted.</q> See <hi>R. B</hi>'s. <hi>Anarchy,</hi> pag. 39.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Thirdly, In</hi> R. B's. Anarchy, <hi>page</hi> 48, 'tis thus written; 'Whether the Church of Chriſt have power in caſes that are matters of conſcience, to give poſitive ſentence or deciſion, which may be obligatory upon belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers?</q> 
               <hi>The Anſwer is in theſe words.</hi> J anſwer affirmatively ſhe hath.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Fourthly, In</hi> R. B's. Anarchy, <hi>pag.</hi> 68, 'tis thus aſſerted; There never will, nor can be wanting in caſe of controverſy, the Spirit of God to give Judgment, through ſome or other, in the Church of Chriſt, ſo long as any Aſſembly can properly, or in any tollerable ſuppoſition, be ſo termed. <hi>Secondly,</hi> that God ordinarily hath employed ſuch, whom he hath made uſe of in gathering his Church, though not excluding others. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That their, <hi>de facto,</hi> giving a poſitive Judgment in ſuch caſes, will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Tyranny &amp; Uſurpation, neither will the pretences of any contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, or refuſing to ſubmit on the account they ſee it not, excuſe them of being guilty of diſobeying God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What greater Door can be opened to blind obedience? and yet the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid doctrines are Vindicated by <hi>G. W.</hi> and his brethren, under the Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of being the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo conſequently inveſted with the authority before aſſerted, but the actions of ſome of <hi>George Whiteheads</hi> brethren eſpouſed by him, have proved them to have been the <hi>Synagogue</hi> of <hi>Satan;</hi> and therefore on due conſideration of the preceding Citations, may not an honeſt man of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> reaſonably thus ſay unto my adverſaries? How unjuſt have you been in repreſenting our Church as being kin to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for a <hi>ſmall Ceremony,</hi> and yet have had the impudence to account your ſelves defamed, when juſtly compared to her? Doth it not now appear that your Principles ſmell too rank of <hi>Popery;</hi> and that not in a <hi>Ceremony</hi> or ſome little <hi>Circumſtance,</hi> but in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> whereby the very life and props of the <hi>Romiſh See</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> (oppoſed by <hi>Reformed Proteſtants,</hi>) is aſſerted and vindicated. Thus much as to <hi>G. W.</hi> and his brethrens <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I ſpeak of the Practical Part of their Religion, I ſhall put the Reader in mind that where ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ward forcible Power is wanting; a falſe Church cannot ſeize the Body and Eſtate: No thanks therefore to <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> who wanting ſuch power, do not ſo do. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> though
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31228:2"/> inveſted with outward power was not guilty of that, untill ſuch time ſhe promulgated ſuch kind of <hi>Doctrine</hi> as before is cited; and that with appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to her ſelf, even as <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> terming themſelves the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> deſignes theſe with application to themſelves, and not to advance either the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus premiſed, I ſhall add a few inſtances of a lower ſort of <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> being the utmoſt that <hi>G. W.</hi> and his brethren are capable to inflict, <hi>viz. Excomunications,</hi> or what imports the ſame, together with Notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Undeſerved <hi>Defamations</hi> being one Practical Part of their Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. B.</hi> by a Meeting in <hi>London</hi> was Excomunicated ſo far as <hi>Excomunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> can be imported, by theſe words, viz. <hi>That we do not only teſtify againſt that Spirit which hath, as aforeſaid, led him into that diſorderly Practice, but alſo againſt him whilſt joyned thereunto, nor can we have Spiritual Communion and Fellowſhip with him, untill unfeignedly he ſhall return unto the Truth by Condemnation of that work and ſpirit.</hi> See <hi>F. B. de Chriſtiana Libertate. p.</hi> 198, 199. Note the diſorderly Practice and Work was (as their paper expreſly ſignifies) his diſperſing into ſeveral Parts of this Nation my Books, ſtiled the <hi>Chriſtian Quaker.</hi> But in their Paper they do not inſert one ſentence thereof, as demonſtration, that the Book was erroneous. Oh deed of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! And though they exorted him, when before them, to condemn what he had done, and read ſome <hi>Objections</hi> to part of the Book; yet refuſed to give him Copy thereof, though frequently demanded by him; further adding as an inducement to anſwer his demand, that if he found the <hi>Objections</hi> to be as they ſaid, he ſhould readily joyn with them in condemning what ever ſhould appear to be evil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. W.</hi> and his brethren, vindicate a Paper given forth by <hi>C. M.</hi> and 65 more againſt <hi>John Wilkinſon</hi> and <hi>John Story,</hi> proved in my ſeventh part of my <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> pag. 22 to be worſe in ſome reſpect than the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Leo</hi> againſt <hi>Martin Luther.</hi> My words on that occaſion are as followeth. In the Paper given forth by <hi>C. M.</hi> and 65 more againſt <hi>John Wilkinſon</hi> and <hi>John Story,</hi> treated on in the ſecond part of the <hi>Chriſtian Quaker.</hi> pag. 92. 'tis thus ſaid, And <hi>we do hereby reprove and judge that Jealous Rending and ſeperate ſpirit, and them (meaning J. W. and J. S.) and their ſeperate Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and that by the ſpirit and power of God, and we warn all unto whom this comes to beware of the ſaid J. S. and J. W. whoſe way at preſent, is not the way of peace.</hi> Whoſoever peruſeth the ſaid paper may percieve it in ſome reſpect much like the <hi>Bull</hi> given forth by <hi>Pope LEO,</hi> the tenth <hi>Anno</hi> 1520. againſt <hi>M. Luther,</hi> but yet in one m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greatly differs. For in the <hi>Bull</hi> againſt <hi>M. L.</hi> there are 42 Articles of <hi>Doctrine</hi> condemned, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Bull</hi> ordered to be read in every place to the intent that the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter for which he was proſecuted, as an Heretick, might be known; but in the aforeſaid Paper ſubſcribed by <hi>C. M. &amp;c.</hi> there is no mention of any particular <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Vitiouſneſs</hi> in life for which they are perſecuted by their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31228:3"/> but inſtead thereof theſe general Recriminations, viz. <hi>That they have evil deſignes and perſevere in them, by word, writing, and Practice, &amp;c.</hi> See alſo more on this Subject in the ſecond part of my <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> pag. 80. Had <hi>G. W</hi>'s. brethren (whoſe practice againſt <hi>J. W.</hi> and <hi>J. S.</hi> he hath vindicated) been but as plain as <hi>Leo</hi> was, the ſpiritual Cheat would have long ſince been more obvious: and though <hi>G. W.</hi> in his <hi>Judgment Fixed,</hi> pag. 16.17. takes notice of the above compariſon, yet amidſt all his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to Divinity and Law, the greateſt arguments brought by him to invalidate the force of the ſaid compariſon, are theſe enſuing Queſtions, viz. <hi>And is not this matter of fact to ſet up a Standard of ſeperation? Where then is his compariſon between Pope LEO the tenth and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, and how was the Pope's Proceedings more juſt?</hi> For theſe impertinent queſtions I may reckon with him a little more anon.</p>
            <p>Next, take an inſtance of one amongſt many more of his Notorious Lyes, pag. 59. he thus ſaith, <q>Seeing W. <hi>R.</hi> eſteemes the <hi>Popes</hi> (yea even the worſt of them) good enough to bring us in compariſon with, and to cite and make them as inſtance againſt us; as <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, pag. 6.22. Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third, pag. 19. and 28. <hi>Julius</hi> the third pag. 31. it may not be amiſs to give ſome deſcription of theſe Popes according to a late Hiſtory or Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract of the lives of the Popes printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1679. (<hi>and then G. W. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to ſignify that Leo</hi> was rankt amongſt <hi>Athieſts.</hi> That <hi>Paul</hi> the Third was rankt amongſt <hi>Magicians, Conjurers, Warryers, Blood-ſuckers, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racides, Jmpoyſoners</hi> and <hi>Favourites,</hi> of <hi>Whores.</hi> That <hi>Julius</hi> the Third was rankt amongſt <hi>Sodomites (adding inſtances to prove them ſuch and having ſo done, doth, pag.</hi> 55. <hi>thus query</hi>) What worſe Perſons upon Earth, could our Adverſary have compared <hi>G. F.</hi> and our Friends unto, or brought in compariſon againſt them in Church <hi>Proccedings</hi> or <hi>Spiritual Cenſures,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his horrid Injuſtice and Envy.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Inſtead of a large Comment on this notorious Falſhood I ſhall tranſcribe what I wrote in my ſeventh Part of the <hi>Chriſtian Quaker</hi> wherein the Names of Pope <hi>Paul,</hi> and Pope <hi>Julius</hi> are inſerted, and leave <hi>G. W.</hi> to be further corrected by his Brethren, according to his merit.</p>
            <p>Pag. 19. <q>What difficulty there may be for one of the <hi>Laity</hi> to have a juſt Hearing and Redreſs in <hi>Rome,</hi> upon a complaint to be made againſt the Pope, I will not pretend to be fully acquainted with; yet, this I know, that a Cry for Juſtice, when relating to <hi>G. F.</hi> hath not been hearkened to in <hi>London,</hi> by one Part of the people, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> unto whom I have addreſſed. See <hi>Preface,</hi> and <hi>Poſtcript</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtian Quaker</hi> in 5. Parts. 'Tis well if the Endeavours of the Penman (<hi>meaning the unnamed Author of the</hi> Accuſer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) who peradventure may expect <hi>Advance</hi> in the Goverment contended for; be not as great to keep off the <hi>ſtroke</hi> of Juſtice, when relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>G. F.</hi> as Card. <hi>Scombergs,</hi> were to keep off the <hi>Reformation</hi> from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31228:3"/> Court of <hi>Rome</hi> in the dayes of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, not knowing how ſoon it might be his own turn to aſcend the <hi>Papal Chair.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In the 27th. page I cited an Agreement, or Order, made at a <hi>Quarterly-Meeting</hi> at <hi>Ralph Fretwell's,</hi> in <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> the 23d. day of the 10th. Month, 1680, in theſe words: <q>I deſire to give up my whole Concern, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, both <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Spiritual,</hi> unto the Judgment of the Spirit of God in the <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women's-Meetings,</hi> as believing it to be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Univerſal Wiſdom of God, than any particular Meaſure in my ſelf, or any Particular's with which the <hi>Men's</hi> and <hi>Women's Meetings</hi> have not Unity.</q> On this occaſion, I ſignified, that <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. wrote to the Perſons concerned, and did not only call them, <hi>Dear Friends;</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, <hi>That the Spirit of God hath given them Life, and will bring them to the City of the Living God, the Heavenly Jeruſalem, and Church of the Firſt Born, which are written in Heaven.</hi> And ſo ſubſcribes in theſe words: <hi>Your dear Friends and Brethren in our Lord Jeſus, in whom you have Life, Peace, and Salvation.</hi> On theſe words, unto which <hi>G. F.</hi> and <hi>G. W.</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed their Names, I thus obſerved; <q>This ſhows no Diſlike to the ſaid Paper, nor yet Diſ-unity with the Perſons; and yet they in other parts ſeem to diſlike the wording thereof: for in their <hi>Letter</hi> to them, they alſo thus ſay;</q> 
               <hi>Now, Dear Friends, if this Order, or Judgment ſhould come into the hands of any Apoſtates, or Oppoſers, they will make ill work with it, and ſay, we ſet up an Arbitrary Power over Men's Conſciences and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in an Implicit Faith and Submiſſion, without inward Conviction,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and that it was like the</hi> Scotch-Covenant. Then I made this further Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <q>This ſhews their ſenſe what <hi>Apoſtates</hi> may ſay, but doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that ſuch their <hi>Saying</hi> might be rational: And why ſo? That's a Secret I will not pretend to be revealed to me: but yet I might have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Caſe amongſt the aforeſaid Inſtances, wherein they were at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> or <hi>Diſunion</hi> with the <hi>Papiſtical</hi> Party; &amp; doubtleſs, in one of them I might have hit the Mark. For I well remember, that <hi>Petro Soave Pola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> in his Hiſtory of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> informs theſe latter Ages, that in the days of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, great <hi>Zeal</hi> was raiſed in ſome, that a <hi>Reformation</hi> might begin in his own Houſe [meaning the <hi>Court of Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſters</hi> moſt immediately relating to him.] And though he did not poſitively contradict a <hi>Reformation,</hi> when a true Repreſentation of matters, worthy thereof, were preſented before him; yet the Policy of that day admitted of no real <hi>Reformation,</hi> but inſtead thereof, only a meer noiſe of what was repreſented as worthy of Amendment, was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to go abroad in <hi>Germany,</hi> &amp;c amongſt the diſcontented Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty, expecting a <hi>Reformation;</hi> but no Proſecution unto a real and thorow Amendment. And, why ſo? This, amongſt others, was one expreſs reaſon, <hi>That it would give occaſion to the</hi> Lutherans <hi>to brag, that they had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31228:4"/> enforced the</hi> Pope <hi>to make that</hi> Reformation. (Further adding) <hi>That by the</hi> Reformation <hi>'twould be confeſſed, that the things provided againſt, were deſervedly reprehended by the</hi> Lutherans. Which would be a great abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to their whole Doctrine. Had the Party eſpouſing the Pope's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, ſaid, 'Twould give occaſion to <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> or <hi>Oppoſers</hi> (for ſuch the <hi>Lutherans</hi> were accounted) to make ill work with it, it would then have been as pertinent an Example in <hi>Terminis,</hi> to ſhew a Union, as now 'tis doubted, 'twill appear in ſubſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Twas a notable aim, indeed, to aim at a Power over Perſons both in their <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> Concerns. <hi>[Mark]</hi> 'twas not over a <hi>Tenth</hi> part, that might have been accounted <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> or like the Prieſts, but over their whole Concern in <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> Concerns. <hi>Moreover,</hi> pag. 30. <hi>I thus proceeded:</hi> What are the <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Tokens</hi> obſerved by <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Party, as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the term <hi>Apoſtate</hi> in their ſence. <hi>To which I thus anſwered:</hi> I will not undertake to give an anſwer in the largeſt extent of their meaning; but yet from the aforeſaid Record of Diſ-union with <hi>John Anſloe</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in Marriage, compared with the <hi>Quarterly-Meetings</hi> Refuſal to read a Paper of ſome Friends Complaint againſt the ſaid <hi>Record,</hi> telling them, (on that occaſion) they were all deceived, or deluded; doth, at leaſt, give a juſt cauſe of Suſpition, that the Non-acceptance of any Such new Order or Preſcription from <hi>G. F.</hi> or the <hi>General-Meeting,</hi> hath been deemed matter of <hi>Apoſtacy:</hi> if ſo, I muſt then ſay, that our Adverſaries have therein exceeded in their Impoſitions, the Doctrine held forth by ſome of the very <hi>Romiſh Religion</hi> it ſelf.</q> 
               <hi>And then I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to give an Inſtance in theſe words;</hi> 
               <q>'Twas the Plea of the Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of the <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the time of Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the Third, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1551, with reſpect to the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> that though the Authority of the whole Univerſality is transferred into the <hi>Major</hi> Part, when the Cauſe is common to all, and nothing belongeth to particular men; yet, when the <hi>Whole</hi> belongeth to all, and every one hath his part, the aſſent of every one is neceſſary, <hi>&amp; prohibentis conditio potior;</hi> and the abſent not giving their <hi>Voices,</hi> are not bound: Of this ſort are <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Aſſemblies;</hi> and be the <hi>Council</hi> as populous as it will, the abſent <hi>Churches</hi> are not bound, if they think ſit not to receive it. This hath always been uſed in ancient Times; That the <hi>Councils</hi> being ended, the <hi>Decrees</hi> ſhould be ſent to be Confirmed by the <hi>Churches</hi> that were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; in which, otherwiſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y had had no Force: which every one that readeth <hi>Hillarius, Athanaſius, Theodoretus,</hi> and <hi>Victorinus,</hi> (who handle this Particular) may ſee plainly; and it happened ſometimes, that ſome part of the <hi>Cannons</hi> were received by ſome <hi>Churches,</hi> and ſome left out, as every one thought ſit for their Neceſſities, Manners, and Uſes: And Sir <hi>Gregory</hi> himſelf doth witneſs, That the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31228:4"/> the <hi>Cannons</hi> of the ſecond <hi>Council</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> nor of the firſt of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> This, I ſuppoſe, the Learned <hi>R. Richardſon,</hi> to whoſe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients</hi> (ſufficiently <hi>Papiſtical</hi>) the <hi>Penman</hi> hath referred, knows to be true, and is now cited on this Occaſion, that the Impartial Reader may conſider, whether, in the moſt charitable Conſtruction of <hi>G. F.</hi> or his Party's Actions, under the Form of <hi>Government</hi> contended for, they have not (notwithſtanding the <hi>Penman's</hi> Deteſtation of <hi>Popery</hi>) gone one large ſtep, in point of <hi>Impoſition,</hi> beyond what is allowed by the Doctrine of ſome, owning the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> to be the <hi>Apoſtolick See.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt not, but that every Impartial Reader will hence diſcern <hi>G. W</hi>'s great Injuſtice, by accuſing me of horrid Injuſtice and Envy, as aforeſaid, for my thus writing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. W.</hi> ſeems (<hi>pag.</hi> 49.50.) to be much diſturbed at one or two Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences in the <hi>Seventh Part</hi> of my <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> pag. 20. Therein I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, <q>That the Biſhop of <hi>Bitonto,</hi> in an <hi>Oration</hi> in relation to the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> and Commendation of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, exhorts all to ſubmit themſelves to that <hi>Council;</hi> which, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> if they do not, it will be juſtly ſaid, <hi>The Popes Light is come into the World, and Men love Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs better than Light.</hi> And then I thus proceeded: Whether that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion may be a proper <hi>Looking-Glaſs</hi> for the <hi>Penman</hi> and <hi>G. F.</hi> to ſee their Faces in, when they conclude it the Fruit of Darkneſs, not to ſubmit to their <hi>Councils</hi> and <hi>Outward Directories,</hi> I ſhall leave to the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the unprejudiced underſtanding Reader,</q> with this further Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <q>That <hi>G. F.</hi> when accounted a Miniſter of Chriſt's Light, did then ſignifie, <hi>That 'twas below Wiſdom to jangle about Outward Things.</hi> And yet ſince hath been a great Inſtrument to cauſe <hi>Janglings</hi> about ſuch things. On this Occaſion <hi>G. W.</hi> pag. 49. 50. thus ſaith; <hi>What a falſe Looking-Glaſs haſt thou repreſented here! Thou mayſt remember that our frequent Teſtimony hath been, and ſtill is, to excite People to Chriſt's Light within, as being that true Light which is come into the World, and to his Council that proceeds from his light and not to the Popes or any of his Councils.</hi>
               </q> Who ſo ignorant, that cannot ſee the <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> contained in this Anſwer: I am well ſatisfied, their ſin is not a <hi>deſign</hi> to be under the ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a <hi>Pope</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> Oh! that they were but as free from <hi>Luſting</hi> after the like Power that he and his Cardinals are inveſted with; if they were, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks <hi>G. W.</hi> who, I ſuppoſe, from his rendering <hi>F. B.</hi> a Fool, hate, not to be accounted witty; ſhould, on this occaſion, have inſerted (inſtead of theſe words, and not to the <hi>Pope,</hi> or any of his <hi>Counſel</hi>) ſuch an expreſſion as this and not to <hi>G. F.</hi> above another; as if our deſires were to teſtify againſt a <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet plead for one ſet, or to be ſet up amongſt our ſelves, nor yet to the <hi>Second-days Meeting;</hi> as if we were againſt the power of the Cardinals at <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet execiſe the like (ſo far as capable) amongſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31228:5"/> ſelves: had he ſo ſaid, and accordingly, for the future, acted, it might have removed many a <hi>Stumbling-block</hi> out of the way.</p>
            <p>And ſince <hi>G. W.</hi> accounts <hi>F. B.</hi> a Fool, as before is ſignified; ſurely then <hi>G. W.</hi> takes himſelf to be a wiſe Man; which occaſions me to examine how wiſe he may be eſteemed amongſt witty and honeſt men: for Children and Fools may be pleaſed with <hi>Hobby-horſes,</hi> and Knaves may applaud <hi>Forgery</hi> and <hi>Perverſion</hi> for <hi>Sound Truths. First,</hi> then note, that if I had compared <hi>G. F. G. W.</hi> and their Friends to any Action committed by Pope <hi>Julius,</hi> &amp;c. that had not been juſtifyable, he ſhould have detected me thereof: but that being wanting, a witty man on ſight of <hi>G. W</hi>'s Book, may conclude, that there was ſome Compariſon made, and that 'twas a true one: if ſo, would it not naturally follow, that <hi>G. W.</hi> &amp;c. in ſuch a witty man's ſenſe, are as bad as thoſe <hi>Popes</hi> rank't by him among <hi>Atheists, Magicians, Conjurers, Warriers, Blood-Suckers, Paracides,</hi> though not directly, or indirectly ſo accuſed by me.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Righteous Account</hi> of <hi>G. W.</hi> renders him a Notorious Falſe <hi>Accuſer,</hi> a Scandal to the Profeſſion of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently inclin'd, as well as gifted to write Books wrongfully, to ſtain the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the men of his Indignation: I hope, his brethren, for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will be aſhamed to ſit under his <hi>Phariſaical</hi> Miniſtry, whil'ſt no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction is given by his real Repentance for the Errors and evil Facts whereof he is guilty; eſpecially, if the ſenſe of his Guilt be ſo great, as to decline the publick <hi>Meeting</hi> (herein after propoſed) for the clearing of himſelf, if he can.</p>
            <p>I now come to prove <hi>G. W.</hi> a publick <hi>Informer</hi> againſt <hi>W. P.</hi> which I term, <hi>to his Defamation,</hi> becauſe the Matter of Fact whereof he ſtands ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, is in ſome reſpect more condemnable than a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Practice deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtified againſt by Reformed <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Now to the Matter in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 61. <hi>G. W.</hi> infers from my words, that they who ſubſcribed the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per againſt <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> being 66 in number, were Perſecutors of their Brethren: and then affirms (without Evidence) that I know <hi>W. P.</hi> to be one. The ſaid Paper againſt <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> is already proved to be worſe, in ſome reſpect, than the <hi>Bull</hi> given forth by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the 10th. againſt <hi>M. Luther.</hi> And <hi>G. W.</hi> hath not written one word that really evidences my ſaid Compariſon untrue: what I take to be the Force of his Argument, will hereafter follow: beſides, 'tis worthy Obſervation, that the ſaid Paper was directed to <hi>Mens-Meetings;</hi> who are therein exhorted to warn <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> where-ever they come, to go home, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therein, ſay they, you will acquit your ſelves in Gods Sight. From which Exhortations 'tis evident, that the Subſcribers of the ſaid Paper, which <hi>G. W.</hi> vindicates, endeavoured to impoſe on the Perſons to whom
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31228:5"/> they wrote, exhorting them to wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>J.</hi> S. and <hi>J. W.</hi> as aforeſaid, and that without leaving the Perſons ſo exhorted to a <hi>Convincement</hi> in themſelves, that their ſo doing might be <hi>Christian-like;</hi> but inſtead thereof, gives them this aſſurance, namely, <hi>That therein you will acquit yourſelves in Gods Sight.</hi> From all which, 'tis evident, that if <hi>W. P.</hi> did ſubſcribe the ſaid Paper, he then merited the afore-mentioned Reflections limited to that Matter, for ſo doing; and in particular, theſe two things might then be laid to his charge. <hi>First,</hi> That he was concerned in a Paper importing <hi>Excomunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> though not ſo termed; and that againſt two antient Miniſters, without mentioning therein any particular matter of <hi>falſe Doctrine,</hi> or <hi>evil Fact</hi> vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated by <hi>J. S.</hi> &amp; <hi>J. W. Secondly,</hi> That his endeavouring, that ſuch to whom 'twas directed, ſhould warn them to go home, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as aforeſaid, implies a deſign of <hi>Impoſition</hi> without <hi>Conviction,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Justification</hi> of <hi>Implicit Faith</hi> &amp; <hi>Obedience,</hi> both which took their <hi>Riſe</hi> from the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and was, and yet is hateful to the <hi>true Reformed Protestants.</hi> That now the Reader may know the force of <hi>G. W</hi>'s <hi>Argument</hi> againſt my <hi>Compariſon,</hi> take it in his own words, pag. 61. <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>As for their not mentioning any particular <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> or <hi>vitious Life,</hi> that others might know the Matters alledged againſt them, what wouldſt infer? That therefore the Popes <hi>Bull</hi> againſt <hi>M. Luther</hi> was more reaſonable or juſt. That's a miſtake, for thou confeſſedſt a <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> given againſt that <hi>Jealous, Rending,</hi> and <hi>Seperate Spirit,</hi> from which thou haſt not cleared them: and was that no reaſon then, to give others Notice and Warning againſt ſuch a Spirit:</q> Is <hi>Schiſm</hi> no ſin, or not reproveable? This occaſions me thus to ſay, <hi>G. W.</hi> is not ſo plain as <hi>Bonner,</hi> for he uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally told the <hi>Protestants</hi> for what he Judged them, and was not aſhamed of the <hi>Pope's</hi> Cauſe; if he deſigned to judge or reprove men for not owning the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Clergy</hi> to be the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and that they ought to believe as the <hi>Church</hi> believed, he would have plainly ſaid ſo, and not inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, tell them, I judge you for being of a <hi>Jealous, Rending,</hi> and <hi>Seperate Spirit.</hi> This, in <hi>Bonner,</hi> without <hi>Explanation;</hi> would have been called <hi>Canting Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage;</hi> and until <hi>G. W.</hi> doth explain his meaning by thoſe words, he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects himſelf to Deriſion and Scorn; and though he hath inſinuated, that I compared him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to a <hi>Pope</hi> rank't amongſt <hi>Conjurers,</hi> yet he wrongs me therein; and I muſt confeſs, that his aforeſaid Argument is no grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sign of a <hi>Conjurer.</hi> But notwithſtanding <hi>G. W.</hi> hath informed, as aforeſaid, againſt <hi>W. P.</hi> yet <hi>W. P</hi>'s. <hi>Addreſs to Protestants,</hi> afterward Printed, <hi>Anno</hi> 1679, cleared him from all ſuch <hi>Pernicious Principles,</hi> that <hi>G. W.</hi> as before is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, vindicates, and ſuch <hi>Rome-like Practices,</hi> tending to Bondage, as <hi>G. W.</hi> is become an Eſpouſer of, by owning himſelf one with, if not one of thoſe that ſubſcribed the Paper againſt <hi>J.</hi> S. and <hi>J. W.</hi> though he pretended to this Purpoſe, that he was moved or warned of God, not to ſubſcribe the ſame: I ſhall quote a few words out of <hi>W. P</hi>'s. <hi>Addreſs</hi> to <hi>Protestants,</hi> to ſhew <hi>W. P</hi>'s. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſe in his own words, pag. 149. 150. <hi>For all Societies are to govern themſelves according to their Institution, and firſt Principles of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where there is a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolence on this part, Tyranny, and not Order, is introduced.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31228:6"/> Now ſince Perſwaſion and Conviction began all true Christian Societies, all Chriſtian Societies must uphold themſelves upon the ſame free Bottom, or they turn Antichristian.</hi> Pag. 186. <hi>The Apostle requires not men to receive him without Evidence, and refers them to that in their own Conſciences in the Sight of God.</hi> Many more <hi>Instances</hi> might be cited, to ſhew <hi>W. P</hi>'s Deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Popiſh-like, enſlaving Principles,</hi> and <hi>Practices;</hi> though <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> now ſinking in his Reputation as a Chriſtian, ſeems to ſhelter himſelf under the Umbrage of <hi>W. P.</hi> Such mean tricks may get <hi>G. W.</hi> a Name, with ſuch an one as he ſcornfully terms <hi>F. B.</hi> namely, a <hi>Fool,</hi> but not with men of Underſtanding, Honeſty, and good Conſcience. But if <hi>W. P.</hi> hath been the Author of any thing Printed ſince his <hi>Addreſs,</hi> &amp;c. whereby his aforeſaid <hi>Aſſertions</hi> are deny'd, or weaken'd, far be it from me to term any man, manifeſting the ſame, an <hi>Informer</hi> to his Defamation, whil'ſt perſiſting therein; for I have had my ſhare in <hi>Detecting</hi> (by the 8th. Part of my <hi>Christian-Quaker</hi>) ſome Principles, or Aſſertions reputed his, that are not now to my purpoſe to treat on; and not having any Reply from him, in diſlike of what I wrote, <hi>Charity</hi> obliges me to ſuppoſe, that (if his Name was not wrongfully made uſe of) it hath been inſtrumental to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince his Conſcience of the Truths vindicated by me.</p>
            <p>Now take an Inſtance of <hi>G. W</hi>'s ſcurrilous Language againſt my ſelf, &amp;c. namely, <hi>Their inſolent Abuſes, cruel Envy, Outrage, Madneſs, and Confuſions of certain Perſons, turned Apoſtate Informers, treacherous Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, falſe Brethren, deceitful Workers, betraying Iudaſes, Devils incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, who have loſt their firſt Love to truth, become degenerate, without natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Affection, Dogs that are without, Wolves, Raging Waves of the Sea.</hi> See his Introductory Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. W.</hi> is not only contented ſo to fame himſelf, as a <hi>Church Governour,</hi> but he hath alſo ſo confidently diſcours't of <hi>Skill</hi> in <hi>Law,</hi> as that he is taken to aim at the Repute of being a very <hi>Learned Lawyer:</hi> How ſo? The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Penman of the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> turned my word <hi>Concerned</hi> into <hi>Repreſented,</hi> and as ſuch treats thereon. On that Occaſion I replyed thus; It may be ſaid of many Thouſands of our Viſible Native Country-men, that they are at ſome times, and ſeaſons exerciſed in an outward Order, under the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King; but if thence they ſhould declare, that they are the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives</hi> of the King's Government, 'twould be deemed a mode of Speech tending to the Annihilating of the King's <hi>Prerogative.</hi> For this, <hi>G. W.</hi> thus treats me, <hi>Herein the man is under a mistake, in this Alluſion his Skil in the Law and the King's Prerogative and Government has failed him.</hi> The truth is, I gave no Inſtance to illuſtrate my Aſſertion; I ſhall now ſupply that defect, by inſtancing one thing amongſt many that might be mentioned. Many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of our Native Country-men, are, on the 1st day of the Week, exerciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in an orderly manner, in hearing and uttering Religious Service, eſtabliſh'd by Law under the King's Government.</p>
            <p>Of all theſe it may be ſaid, That they are exerciſed in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31228:6"/> an Outward Order, under the Government of the King; but it cannot be ſaid of all ſuch, that they are Repreſentatives of the King's Government, which chiefly is repreſented in his Courts. Methinks <hi>G. W.</hi> ſhould be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his ridiculous Oppoſition on the foot of his Skill in Law, for that by a contrary <hi>Aſſertion</hi> to what I laid down, every common <hi>Porter</hi> (if a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive) exerciſed as aforeſaid, might then be declared a Repreſentative of the King's Government, though no legal Officer. This puts me in mind to note, that <hi>G. W.</hi> hath lately publiſh't in his Name, a Book, ſtiled, <hi>Due Order of Law and Justice, against irregular and arbitrary Proceedings.</hi> I ſhall a little examine how well ſuch a Title becomes his Book. He oppoſed giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>J. B.</hi> Copy of the <hi>Meeting's Objections</hi> againſt my Book; for the ſpreading whereof, he was declared againſt, as aforeſaid: this was ſign of great Diſorder and Injuſtice in <hi>G. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>G. W.</hi> handles the Matter of Law well, I know he muſt then thereby condemn his own, and his Brethren's Practices: if ill, then it may become a ſhame to put ſuch a Title, by which he may obtain the Repute of a <hi>Learned Lawyer,</hi> from ſuch as know him not. <hi>(O proud Conceited Man!)</hi> Even as <hi>G. F.</hi> was reputed to be inſpired with the <hi>Knowledge of Tongues,</hi> by ſubſcribing to many framed Sentences in divers Languages; (witneſs his <hi>Battledore</hi>) though he is not gifted to write, or ſpeak ſenſe in his <hi>Mother-Tongue,</hi> in a Through-Diſcourſe, or Debate on ſome Subjects, if ſome of his Books and publick Diſcourſes may be thought a proper Proof in the Caſe. The remembrance of this can never credit <hi>G. W</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on <hi>F. B.</hi> for want of Schollarſhip.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now add ſomething touching <hi>G. W</hi>'s <hi>Hypocritical, Phariſaical Spirit,</hi> though he is guilty in divers parts of his Treatiſe, of many Errors more than this Paper detects him of; yet, at length, he ſpeaks on this wiſe; <q>Thou knoweſt, O Lord, that though thou haſt endued me with a Chriſtian Spirit, and with Faith, Patience, and rejoycing under all my Sufferings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet, thou haſt alſo endued me with the Spirit of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgment, Underſtanding, and Zeal for the Glory of thy Holy Name and Truth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Methinks <hi>G. W.</hi> ſhould have conſidered, that though he may deceive Fools, and have now and then a Smile from a <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> yet that God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deceived by telling him a parcel of Lyes; but his great Sin is, his (as it were) calling God to witneſs, by ſaying, <hi>Thou knoweſt;</hi> when in reality, 'twas in a Caſe wherein a notorious Lye dropt from his Pen; for his very Book will appear in Judgment againſt him, that at the penning thereof he was far remote from acting the part of a Righteous Judge. And many Inſtances, not herein cited, might be collected to prove the ſame: 'tis ſo notoriouſly wicked, that 'tis no marvel to me, that <hi>G. W.</hi> juſtifies the unnam'd <hi>Penman</hi> of the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> (pag. 52.) though, by <hi>W. P</hi>'s Rule in his <hi>Winding-Sheet</hi> for <hi>Controverſy Ended,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Penman,</hi> for not putting his Name to his Work, may be compared to a very <hi>Night-bird,</hi> a <hi>Wanderer,</hi> one that looks and creeps up and down like a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31228:7"/> 
               <hi>Vagrant.</hi> And though in the <hi>Seventh Part</hi> of my <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> an <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Cry</hi> is recorded after the Name of the <hi>Penman;</hi> yet, I ſuppoſe, <hi>G. W.</hi> was aſham'd, or afraid to become an <hi>Informer</hi> in that Caſe, by a poſitive Diſcovery of the Man's Name. His Confeſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 52. that he hath a ſhare therein, and ſees no cauſe to retract, but ſtand by it; is no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Diſcovery.</p>
            <p>I hope <hi>G. W.</hi> will accept theſe few Lines as a ſufficient SCOURGE, to correct a part of his Errours, and to abate a part of his Wrath, Pride, and Confidence: if not, I now make this offer unto him; That I ſhall be ready to meet him in ſome Publick Place to be agreed upon between us both, where Liberty may be allowed, that any Perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may freely hear; and my end is, that I may then have opportunity, to treat more largely on the foregoing Subjects, and that he, on behalf of himſelf and Brethren, may have opportunity to vindicate themſelves, if he can, from the guilt of Error now laid, or that further may be laid to his charge, by reaſon of what he hath wrote in his Book, Stiled, <hi>Judgment Fixed;</hi> though frequently read, <hi>Judgment Fired:</hi> which would have been a very proper Title to his Bundle of Wrath and Malice. For ſince 'tis ſo, that one Part of the people, called, <hi>Quakers,</hi> are principled from the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond-day Meeting's</hi> approved Councel, not to read my Books, and that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Part need no further evidence to convince them, that <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> ſtand by and eſpouſe a wrong cauſe, and that others termed <hi>Newters</hi> will not concern themſelves in the <hi>Controverſy;</hi> there is no reaſon to trace <hi>G. W.</hi> (nor yet any other) Book againſt me in all it's <hi>Perverſions, falſe Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and other <hi>Evils</hi> and <hi>Errors</hi> by a thorow Anſwer; eſpecially ſince a few lines are ſufficient to manifeſt, that the Root from whence their <hi>Bulky-Rubbiſh</hi> ſprings is evil. The Lord ſoften <hi>G. W</hi>'s <hi>Stony-Heart;</hi> that he may be Converted and Healed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>W. <hi>D.</hi> wrote to <hi>G. W</hi> to know whether he would ſtand by this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> namely, that there can be no <hi>vnity</hi> without <hi>Conformity,</hi> and that the People of God, or Children of God are, or muſt be in <hi>vniformity. G. W.</hi> writes to <hi>W. D.</hi> and cites the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and then adds his anſwer in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe words. <hi>Anſ.</hi> True, 1ſt. <hi>with reſpect to a Conformity to the death of Chriſt, to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Son of God.</hi> 2dly. <hi>They muſt be in vniformity, with reſpect to the vnity of the Spirit, the vnity of the Faith; &amp; being of one Judgment according to their meaſures of Degrees &amp; Growths in Chriſt, as they come to be of one Heart and Soul vnited in Love, there is a vniformity in Subſtance, though not genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y (nor is it required) in all Circumſtances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence I obſerve, that <hi>G. W.</hi> ſtraines the word <hi>vnity</hi> to import <hi>vniformity,</hi> and to be as a Proof that Gods Children are, or muſt be in <hi>vniformity;</hi> and yet he confeſses to Meaſures of <hi>Degrees</hi> and <hi>Growths</hi> in Chriſt, which admits of various Forms; though the <hi>vnity</hi> in <hi>Spirit</hi> may not be broken. Next I obſerve from the latter Part of his words, that there are <hi>Requirers</hi> of <hi>vniformity</hi> in Subſtance, though not generally in all <hi>Circumſtances.</hi> Hence I query, 1ſt. Who hath power so require God's People to be in <hi>vniformity?</hi> 2dly. What are the Subſtantiall Formes that muſt be and can't be diſpens'd with? 3dly. What are the Circumſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Forms that may be diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with, and not required? 4thly. Whence the <hi>Requirers</hi> had their Power to enjoyn <hi>vniformity?</hi> 5thly. Since Chriſt is the Subſtance, whether they are not <hi>vſurpers</hi> who require his members to ſubject to outward Forms, terming ſome <hi>Subſtantial,</hi> and others <hi>Circumſtantial.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31228:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
